A Guide to the George Green Shackelford Papers, 1899-1990 (Bulk 1955-1989)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
George Green Shackelford Papers, 1899-1990 (Bulk, 1955-1989)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1983-008
16.8 cu. ft. 12 Boxes, 7 Oversized Folders
This collection contains correspondence, research files, project files, and manuscripts of George Green Shackelford, professor of history at Virginia Tech from 1954-1986.
Shackelford, George Green
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated in 1983.
Biographical Information
George Green Shackelford was a professor of history at Virginia Tech. He also was a historical preservation expert and specialist in the age of Washington and Jefferson in Virginia history. In 1985, he received an award from the Virginia Chapter of the American Institute of Architecture in historic preservation.
Shackelford attended the Woodberry Forest School, Columbia University, and then the University of Virginia for his Ph.D. He also earned certificates from the Attingham Summer School and Institute of Historical and Archival Management.
In 1942, Shackelford received his commission in the Naval Reserve and served in anti-submarine warfare in the Atlantic and Pacific. He was a Lieutenant by the end of his service.
Before Shackelford taught at Virginia Tech from 1954 to 1986, he taught at Birmingham Southern College from 1948 to 1949 and worked as a research fellow at the Virginia Historical Society. From 1963 to 1964, Shackelford spearheaded the restoration of Smithfield Plantation. In 1967, he worked as a historical consultant to the Westmoreland David Memorial Foundation for Morven Park in Leesburg, Virginia.
Shackelford was also a prolific author. He wrote five books, including Jefferson's Adoptive Son: The Life of William Short, 1759-1849 and Thomas Jefferson's Travels in Europe, 1784-1789. He also wrote many articles and was the co-editor of the Virginia Social Sciences Journal.
Throughout his career, Shackelford was active in numerous associations and boards:
He was the President of the Monticello Association from 1969 to 1971.
He was on the board of directors for APVA, now Preservation Virginia, and was the President of the Montgomery Branch of the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities in 1975.
He was a member of the Board of Advisors of the National Trust for Historical Preservation from 1976 until 1979.
He was a member of the Virginia Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution from 1987 until 1992.
He was the President of the Southwest Virginia Branch of the English Speaking Union.
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials relating George Green Shackelford, a professor of history at Virginia Tech and includes clippings, correspondence, memoranda, bulletins, scrapbooks, and other materials relating to the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities (now Preservation Virginia); the National Trust; the New River Historical Association; the Virginia Landmark Commission the Democratic Committee of Montgomery County (Virginia); the Visiting Scholar Committee of the College of Arts and Sciences for VPI Blacksburg, Virginia, and Southwest Virginia history; historic properties in Blacksburg and Southwest Virginia, particularly Smithfield Plantation; and of Virginia and VPI&SU related topics.
Two notable collection items are a card from Mrs. John F. Kennedy thanking Shackelford for his sympathy for her husband's death and an invite to a reception in honor of Mrs. Douglas MacArthur of The National Officers of the Hereditary Societies of the United States at The Washington Club.
Although most collection items relate to Shackelford's professional and academic career, some notable personal items include local clippings reporting his wedding to Grace Howard McConnell and various invitations to his home for holiday parties. Because Shackelford was a prolific letter writer and maintained close relationships with many of his colleagues, his professional correspondence often includes personal inquiries.
This collection is arranged into six series--Series I: Correspondence; Series II: Manuscripts, Projects, Research, and Academic Papers; Series III: Association papers; Series IV: Personal Papers; Series V: Scrapbooks; and Series IV: Oversized Materials. Within these series, there is some subject overlap within individual folders.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged first by material type, then subject, and then alphabetically. Some subject and series overlap within individual folders.
Series I: Correspondence contains correspondence separated into authors. Where no large group by one author existed, correspondence was arranged in folders in alphabetical order. Efforts were made to separate professional and personal correspondence, but a great deal of overlap remains.
Series II: Manuscripts, Projects, Research, and Academic Papers contains drafts of papers, research materials, and completed papers, arranged in alphabetical order.
Series III: Association Papers contains materials Shackelford kept from the various professional and political groups he associated with, in alphabetical order by group.
Series IV: Personal Papers contains personal materials relating Shackelford and his life, arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series V: Scrapbooks Contains scrapbooks put together by Shackelford of newspaper articles, mostly from the Richmond Times.
Series VI: Oversized Materials contains oversized materials, including newspaper clippings, brochures, and publications, arranged by subject.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Montgomery County Branch Papers, 1754-1996 (Ms1962-001)
George Green Shackelford Student Papers, 1963-1989 (Ms2011-006)
Index Terms
Geographical Names:
Blacksburg, Va
Subjects:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Local Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Faculty; Local/Regional History; Montgomery County (Va.); University Archives
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1939-1990
  - A, 1947-1987 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Adams, Howard, National Gallery of Art, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Alan and Eva Rothschild, 1953-1987 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Albemarle Historical Society, 1955-1983 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Ambery, Charles and Markatos, Spencer, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - American Philosophical Society and Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1954-1959 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - APIVA Request for State and Local Aid, 1980 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - BAA-BAZ, 1959-1988 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Battle, William C., 1967-1970 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Baver, Henry H., VPI, 1978-1985 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - BEA-BIZ, 1958-1989 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Bear, James A., Thomas Jefferson Foundation, 1967-1985 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Berkebile, Downing, and Des Granges, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Block-BZ, 1948-1990 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Boles, John B., 1970-1987 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Bowels, William (Stedman House), 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Bullard, John, 1969 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Bullock, Helen Duprey, National Trust for Historic Preservation, 1961-1978 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Campbell, Peter and Barbados, 1962-1980 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Charles A. Robb and Balilies, 1981-1989 (Box-folder 1-20)
  - CH-CN, 1952-1987 (Box-folder 1-21)
  - COA-CP, 1948-1986 (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Comfort Station Aid Request (Smithfield Plantation), 1980 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Cowan, Walker, 1972-1987 (Box-folder 1-24)
  - CR-CZ, 1956-1986 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - DA-DE, 1950-1989 (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Davis, AK and Horace and Cutris Carroll, 1957-1988 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Davis, Charles Jr., 1961-1965 (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Day, Horace, 1983 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - De Lune, David, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Dix, George and Hounigringer, George, 1967 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Donald G. Weiss & Co., Inc., 1967-1969 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Episcopal Christ Church & Emmanuel Chapel, 1959-1988 (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Fishwick, 1959-1988 (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Fleming, James A., 1963-1976 (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Frank S. Walker Jr., 1960-1985 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Frazier, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - French & Co., 1933-1969 (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Hahn, Harper & Harvard, 1969-1985 (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Hale, Oron J., 1957-1973 (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Henry Taylor Jr., 1971-1985 (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Hereford, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Hunt, Conover, Ralph, about James Madison Exhibition for Library of Congress, 1957, 1975-1982 (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Jeff Turner, 1985 (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Jones, Archer, 1961-1979 (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Jones, Archer, 1981-1990 (Box-folder 2-18)
  - Jones & Landon, 1964-1975 (Box-folder 2-19)
  - Jordan, 1983-1989 (Box-folder 2-20)
  - John Melville Jennings, 1950-1985 (Box-folder 2-21)
  - King, George Harison Stanford, 1963-1979 (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Low, William Goadby, 1955 (Box-folder 2-23)
  - Marye, 1983-1990 (Box-folder 2-24)
  - Mayo, Bernard & Malone, Dumas, 1954-1985 (Box-folder 2-25)
  - Michael Hurst, St. John's College, 1970-1982 (Box-folder 2-26)
  - Miller, 1956-1989 (Box-folder 2-27)
  - Montgomery County, 1958-1972 (Box-folder 3-1)
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 3-2)
  - New River Historical Society, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Northern Neck of VA Historical Society, 1958-1965 (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Orange County Historical Society Newsletters, 1974-1990 (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Otey, Charles, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Party Invitations, 1971 (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Personal - DI-DU, 1962-1988 (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Personal - E, 1956-1990 (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Personal - F, 1946-1990 (Box-folder 3-10)
  - Personal - GA-GQ, 1959-1988 (Box-folder 3-11)
  - Personal - GRA-GZ, 1951-1987 (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Personal - H, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 3-13)
  - Personal - HAA-HAQ, 1935-1988 (Box-folder 3-14)
  - Personal - HAR-HAZ, 1952-1990 (Box-folder 3-15)
  - Personal - HE-HN, 1960-1990 (Box-folder 3-16)
  - Personal - HO-HZ, 1956-1989 (Box-folder 3-17)
  - Personal - I-K, 1953-1990 (Box-folder 3-18)
  - Personal - KA-KF, 1952-1989 (Box-folder 3-19)
  - Personal - LA-LE, 1958-1989 (Box-folder 3-20)
  - Personal - LI-LY, 1966-1990 (Box-folder 3-21)
  - Personal - MA, 1954-1989 (Box-folder 3-22)
  - Personal - MAC-MC, 1957-1990 (Box-folder 4-1)
  - Personal - ME-MN, 1956-1982 (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Personal - N, 1948-1989 (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Personal - O, 1956-1986 (Box-folder 4-4)
  - Personal - P, 1931-1990 (Box-folder 4-5)
  - Personal - R, 1953-1990 (Box-folder 4-6)
  - Personal - SA-SJ, 1954-1986 (Box-folder 4-7)
  - Personal - SIA-SRZ, 1953-1989 (Box-folder 4-8)
  - Personal - T, 1949-1990 (Box-folder 4-9)
  - Personal - U-V, 1961-1988 (Box-folder 4-10)
  - Personal - WA-WI, 1948-1989 (Box-folder 4-11)
  - Personal - WJ-WZ, 1948-1989 (Box-folder 4-12)
  - Personal - X-Z, 1965-1982 (Box-folder 4-13)
  - Powell, Lewis, American Association of State Colleges and Universities, 1968 (Box-folder 4-14)
  - Professional - N-S, 1954-1975 (Box-folder 4-15)
  - Professional - T-Z, 1959-1966 (Box-folder 4-16)
  - Proffit, Alice R., 1968-1970 (Box-folder 4-17)
  - Raab, John, 1959, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 4-18)
  - Rachal, William, Virginia Historical Society, 1954-1984 (Box-folder 4-19)
  - Randolph, John, Jeff, Virgil, 1956-1989 (Box-folder 5-1)
  - Rennolds, 1965-1986 (Box-folder 5-2)
  - Richmond, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 5-3)
  - Roanoke Historical Society, 1967-1990 (Box-folder 5-4)
  - Scully, Leonard, 1967-1979 (Box-folder 5-5)
  - Shackelford Prizes and Scholarship, 1986 (Box-folder 5-6)
  - Spong, William, Senator, 1961-1975 (Box-folder 5-7)
  - STA-SZ, 1951-1990 (Box-folder 5-8)
  - Tenn, LSU, & UNC Presses, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 5-9)
  - Theode, Alfred (US Trust Company), 1967-1970 (Box-folder 5-10)
  - Tyler Thomas, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 5-11)
  - VA History Course at VPI & UVA, 1957-1963 (Box-folder 5-12)
  - Visiting Scholars to VT, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 5-13)
  - Whitehill, Walter Muir, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 5-14)
  - Wilson R. Porterfield, 1967, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 5-15)
  - Winmill Carriage Museum, 1969 (Box-folder 5-16)
  - Wriggins III, Thomas, 1971 (Box-folder 5-17)
  - Wyatt Williams, Jr., 1961-1989 (Box-folder 5-18)
- Series II: Manuscript, Project, Research, and Academic Papers, 1899-1990 Bulk, 1955-1989
  - Age of Washington and Jefferson Class, 1979-1989 (Box-folder 5-19)
  - "A Peep into Elysium" Drafts and Notes Part I, 1971-1987 (Box-folder 5-20)
  - "A Peep into Elysium" Drafts and Notes Part II, 1971-1987 (Box-folder 5-21)
  - Andrew Miller Campaign, 1977 (Box-folder 5-22)
  - American Friends of the Attingham, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 5-23)
  - APIVA Road, 1969-1978 (Box-folder 6-1)
  - Anne Cary Randolph Bankhead Drafts and Notes, 1964 (Box-folder 6-2)
  - Army Corps of Engineers Little Kanawha, West Virginia Project, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 6-3)
  - Army Corps of Engineers West Virginia Project Preliminary Report, 1972 (Box-folder 6-4)
  - "A Traditional Way in Russia" Drafts and Notes, 1989 (Box-folder 6-5)
  - Benjamin Franklin Randolph Paper, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 6-6)
  - Bicentennial Celebration in Southwest Virginia & Fincastle Resolution, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 6-7)
  - Bicentennial in Southwest Virginia, 1975 (Box-folder 6-8)
  - Blacksburg Historic Buildings and Regulations, 1975 (Box-folder 6-9)
  - Blacksburg Sale, Richard, Zoning and Planning, 1967-1980 (Box-folder 6-10)
  - Blue Ridge Springs, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 6-11)
  - Book Notes on Bayne, Denegre Families, 1983 (Box-folder 6-12)
  - Braxton County, West Virginia, n.d. (Box-folder 6-13)
  - Burnsville Reservoir Report, 1971 (Box-folder 6-14)
  - Carriages, 1969-1976 (Box-folder 6-15)
  - Coaching Club, 1935-1967 (Box-folder 6-16)
  - Collected Papers of the Monticello Association - Forward and Table of Contents, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 6-17)
  - Collected Papers of the Monticello Association - Index, n.d. (Box-folder 6-18)
  - Conserve Banks, 1980 (Box-folder 6-19)
  - Conserve Bridges, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 6-20)
  - Conserve Camden, 1968 (Box-folder 6-21)
  - Conserve Churches and Synagogues, 1978 (Box-folder 6-22)
  - Conserve Courthouse, 1979 (Box-folder 6-23)
  - Conserve by Urban Homesteading, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 6-24, Oversize Folder 1)
  - Conserve Hotels, 1979 (Box-folder 6-25)
  - Conserve Movies, Operas, Halls, 1978 (Box-folder 6-26)
  - Conserve Neighborhoods, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 6-27)
  - Conserve Roofs and Siding, 1977 (Box-folder 6-28)
  - Conserve Rural Spaces, 1978-1981 (Box-folder 6-29)
  - Consultant Grants, 1979, 1989 (Box-folder 6-30)
  - Economic Benefits, 1987 (Box-folder 3-31)
  - Edwardian Carriage Book, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 3-32)
  - Ellen, Cornelia and Mary Jefferson, James Madison Randolph Drafts, n.d. (Box-folder 6-33)
  - Faculty Activities Reports, 1944-1955, 1973-1995 (Box-group 6-34)
  - Federal Register, 1974 (Box-folder 6-35)
  - Fellowships, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 6-36)
  - Fincastle County, n.d. (Box-folder 6-37)
  - Fort Defiance, n.d. (Box-folder 6-38)
  - Founder's Day, UVA, 1970 (Box-folder 6-39)
  - Francis Eppes VII Paper Draft, n.d. (Box-folder 7-1)
  - Furniture Restoration, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 7-2)
  - "George Wythe Randolph" Drafts Part I, 1975 (Box-folder 7-3)
  - 'George Wythe Randolph' Drafts Part II, 1975 (Box-folder 7-4)
  - Goodwin, Mills & Morren Park, 1969 (Box-folder 7-5)
  - Government and Preservation, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 7-6, Oversize Folder 1)
  - Grand Central and Overton Park, 1978 (Box-folder 7-7)
  - Hardy County, West Virginia, n.d. (Box-folder 7-8)
  - Harrison County General Notes, n.d. (Box-folder 7-9)
  - Harrison County Deeds 1800's & 1900's, n.d. (Box-folder 7-10)
  - Historic Garden Week in Virginia, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 7-11)
  - "Historic Preservation is a Good Curse" Draft, n.d. (Box-folder 7-12)
  - Historic Preservation and Social Sciences Paper, n.d. (Box-folder 7-13)
  - Historic Preservation Week, 1975 (Box-folder 7-14)
  - Historic Zoning, 1972-1980 (Oversize Folder 1, Box-folder 7-15)
  - History 4104 Historic Preservation, 1972-1990 (Box-folder 7-16)
  - History of the Monticello Graveyard Drafts, n.d. (Box-folder 7-17)
  - Huxtable on Preservation, 1971 (Box-folder 7-18)
  - Interpretation, n.d. (Box-folder 7-19)
  - John Wayles Eppes UVA Masters Thesis Drafts, 1942 (Box-folder 7-20)
  - Lecture Series, 1968 (Box-folder 7-21)
  - Lewis County, Grantor, Grantee, Deeds, n.d. (Box-folder 7-22)
  - Lewis County, West Virginia Notes, 1972, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 7-23)
  - Litte Kanawha Bibliography, 1972 (Box-folder 7-24)
  - Masterplots Book Reviews, n.d. (Box-folder 7-25)
  - Mayonian Fund, 1976-1984 (Box-folder 7-26)
  - McCormick Estate, Walnut Grove, 1958 (Box-folder 7-27)
  - Meriwether Lewis Randolph Drafts, n.d. (Box-folder 7-28)
  - Miller's house (Smithfield Plantation), 1980-1981 (Box-folder 7-29)
  - Monticello Association of Officer Bios, n.d. (Box-folder 7-30)
  - Morven Park Appraisal, 1926 (Box-folder 7-31)
  - Morven Park Appraisal, 1963 (Box-folder 7-32)
  - Morven Park Appraisal, 1967 (Box-folder 7-33)
  - Morven Park Appraisal, 1969 (Box-folder 7-34)
  - Morven Park Formal Opening, 1969 (Box-folder 7-35)
  - Morven Park International Equestrian Institute, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 7-36)
  - Morven Park Masons and Swans, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 7-37)
  - Morven Park Programs, 1969, 1981 (Box-folder 8-1)
  - Murdock, 1977-1984 (Box-folder 8-2)
  - National Jefferson Memorial Address, 1973 (Box-folder 8-3)
  - National Park Service and Heritage Conservation, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 8-4)
  - National Register of Historic Places, 1972 (Box-folder 8-5)
  - National Trust Annual Reports, 1972-1983 (Box-folder 8-6)
  - Nicholas Phillip Trist Drafts, n.d. (Box-folder 8-7)
  - Nicholas B. Trist Papers (photocopies), n.d. (Box-folder 8-8)
  - NANZATICO, Part I, n.d. (Box-folder 8-9)
  - NANZATICO, Part II, n.d. (Box-folder 8-10)
  - Oral History, n.d. (Box-folder 8-11)
  - Preservation at Mary Washington, 1982 (Box-folder 8-12)
  - Preservation Basics, 1979 (Box-folder 8-13)
  - Preservation Bibliography, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 8-14)
  - Preservation Easements, 1989 (Box-folder 8-15)
  - Preservation Education, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 8-16)
  - Perservation Loans and Grants, 1977 (Box-folder 8-17)
  - Roanoke Times Reviews, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 8-18, Oversize Folder 5)
  - Rouge Dragon, 1968 (Box-folder 8-19)
  - Septima Randolph and Meikeleham Drafts, n.d. (Box-folder 8-20)
  - "Short Ridgely Letters" Papers, 1969 (Box-folder 8-21)
  - Smithfield Plantation Archaeological Project, 1975 (Box-folder 8-22)
  - Southwest Virginia in the New York Times, 1980 (Box-folder 8-23)
  - Southwest Virginia Tour Along US 11, 1960-1966, 1978 (Box-folder 8-24)
  - Thomas Jefferson Randolph UVA Dissertation Drafts, n.d. (Box-folder 8-25)
  - Thomas Mann Randolph of Edgehill Drafts, 1950 (Box-folder 8-26)
  - The Private Stable, 1899 (Box-folder 8-27)
  - To Practice Law or Seek Political Preferment Draft Edits, n.d. (Box-folder 8-28)
  - US-USSR Exchange Program, 1959-1964 (Box-folder 8-29)
  - UVA Summer School, 1963 (Box-folder 9-1)
  - Virginia Historical Sites Brochures, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 9-2)
  - Virginia Historic Landmarks Commonwealth, 1966-1982 (Box-folder 9-3)
  - Virginia History 4122 Class, 1982-1989 (Box-folder 9-4)
  - Various Papers and Drafts, 1963, n.d. (Box-folder 9-5)
  - Virginia Tech Student Events, 1965-1970 (Box-folder 9-6)
  - Virginia Tech and UVA News, 1942-1975 (Box-folder 9-7)
  - Virginia Wedding News, 1946-1959 (Box-folder 9-8)
  - VPA Master in History Proposals, 1964-1967 (Box-folder 9-9)
  - Westmoreland Davis Memorial Foundation Insurance, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 9-10)
  - Westmoreland Davis Foundation, Morven Park, 1966-1971 (Box-folder 9-11)
  - West Virginia Environmental Impact Study Specs, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 9-12)
  - William Short Letters, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 9-13)
  - Winmill Carriage Appraisal, 1976 (Box-folder 9-14)
  - Winmill Carriage Museum Ceremonies, 1969 (Box-folder 9-15)
  - Woodberry Forest School, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 9-16)
  - Woodberry Forest School Funding, 1938-1976 (Box-folder 9-17)
  - Younger, Edward Eugene, 1959-1978 (Box-folder 9-18)
- Series III: Association Papers, 1956-1987
  - APVA Annual Tea, 1982 (Box-folder 9-19)
  - APVA Materials, 1978-1982 (Box-folder 9-20)
  - APVA Materials, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 9-21)
  - APVA Membership Polls, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 9-22)
  - APVA of Montgomery County News, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 9-23)
  - Claytor Lake Sailing Club, 1961-1977 (Box-folder 9-24)
  - Democratic Convention, 1968-1976 (Box-folder 9-25)
  - Democrat Literature, 1967-1977 (Box-folder 9-26)
  - Democratic Party of Virginia, 1957, 1967-1976 (Box-folder 10-1)
  - Democrat Promotional Materials, 1965-1976 (Box-folder 10-2)
  - Local Organizations' Invitations and Program Samples, 1966-1980 (Box-folder 10-3)
  - Miscellaneous Political News, 1968-1976 (Box-folder 10-4)
  - Montgomery APIVA Newsletter, 1978-1985 (Box-folder 10-5)
  - Montgomery County Democratic Committee, 1967-1976 (Box-folder 10-6)
  - Montgomery Film Society, 1961-1962, 1975 (Box-folder 10-7)
  - Monticello Association, 1963, 1971 (Box-folder 10-8)
  - Monticello Association Committee Reports, Minutes, and Notes, 1956 (Box-folder 10-9)
  - Monticello Association Member Questionnaire, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 10-10)
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 10-11)
  - Orange County Historical Society, 1974-1986 (Box-folder 10-12)
  - Republican Promotional Materials, 1969-1977 (Box-folder 10-13)
  - Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. Reports to Virginia, 1968-1977 (Box-folder 10-14)
  - The English Speaking Union, 1958-1974 (Box-folder 10-15)
  - The English Speaking Union, 1975-1987 (Box-folder 10-16)
  - The Virginia Association, Tennessee, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 10-17)
  - University Club, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 10-18)
  - Virginia Historical Society, 1961-1988 (Box-folder 10-19)
  - Virginia Social Science Association, 1968,1972 (Box-folder 10-20)
  - Washington County Historical Society, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 10-21)
- Series IV: Personal Papers, 1939-1985
  - Articles about Shackelford, 1966-1976 (Box-folder 10-22)
  - Casa Leona and Blacksburg Properties, 1964-1981 (Box-folder 10-23)
  - General Personal Papers, 1939-1976 (Box-folder 10-24)
  - Marriage to Grace Howard, 1962 (Box-folder 10-25)
  - Musical Performances, Blacksburg and Roanoke, 1952-1966, n.d. (Box-folder 10-26)
  - Virginia Society of American Institute of Architects Preservation Award, 1985 (Box-folder 10-27)
- Series V: Scrapbooks, 1943-1971
  - Newspaper Clippings Scrapbook, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Newspaper Clipping Scrapbook, 1943, 1960-1961 (Box 11)
  - Newspaper Clipping Scrapbook, 1967-1971 (Box 11)
  - Newspaper Clipping Scrapbook, 1969 (Box 12)
  - Spong for U.S. Senate Campaign Scrapbook, 1966 (Box 12)
  - Spong for U.S. Senate Campaign Scrapbook, 1966-1968 (Box 12)
- Series VI: Oversized Materials, 1943-1985
  - Newspaper Clippings Related to Series I, 1959-1981 (Oversize Folder 1)
  - General Brochures, Maps, and Other Oversized Materials, 1968-1985 (Oversize Folder 2)
  - Morven Park Architectural Drawings, n.d. (Oversize Folder 3)
  - Blacksburg Area Transportation Study and Monticello Association Projects, 1968 (Oversize Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings,1943-1977 (Oversize Folder 5)
  - Howell, Henry & Miller, P. Political News Clippings, 1963-1977 (Oversize Folder 6)
  - Smithfield Brochures and News, 1961-1976 (Oversize Folder 7)